<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"> 

<section id="sec_analyseSTGraph">
	<?dbhtml filename="analyseDynamicGraph.html"?>
	<title>Analysing the state transition graph</title>
	<section id="sec_scc">
		<title>Strongly connected components</title>
		<para>GINsim allows to compute the graph of the Strongly Connected Components (SCC
			graph, <emphasis>cf.</emphasis> <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strongly_connected_component"/>)
			of an existing graph, through the <emphasis>SCC graph</emphasis> option of the
			<emphasis>Actions</emphasis> menu. The SCC graph is an acyclic graph abstracted
			from the original one: each node of the SCC graph corresponds to a cycle or a set of intertwined
			cycles of the original graph. The resulting graph is thus usually much more compact.</para>
		<figure id="fig_scc">
			<title>Strongly Connected Components graph</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/scc.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<simpara>Example of Strongly Connected Component Graph (bottom right) and
					the corresponding statetransition graph (top left). 
					The <emphasis>Selection Attribute</emphasis> tab in the bottom panel shows
					the content of the selected SCC (<emphasis>i.e.</emphasis> the list of nodes
					in the original graph).</simpara>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Note that the <emphasis>SCC Graph</emphasis> tool can also be applied to
			regulatory graphs.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_pathFinder">
		<title>Path finder</title>
		<para>The "search path" action enables the determination of paths between pairs of states of the state transition graph.
		Selecting the "search a path" action in the action menu opens a configuration dialog box, which allows the specification
		of a starting state, a target state , and optional intermediate states (using the "+" and "X" buttons to add/remove them).
		GINsim then performs a shortest path search. If several paths exist between these states, the first encountered shortest
		path is returned.</para>
		<figure id="fig_pathFinder">
			<title>Search for a path in the state transition graph</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/search_path.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para>The search tool has found a path from the state
						<emphasis>0110</emphasis> to <emphasis>0311</emphasis>, involving four
						steps.</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_animator" xreflabel="Animation plugin">
		<title>Animation plugin</title>
		<para>The animation tool is launched through the <emphasis>Animate</emphasis> option of
			the <emphasis>Action</emphasis> menu of a state transition graph. It allows to
			interactively follow a trajectory in the state transition graph. Genes of the
			regulatory graph are highlighted, to display the corresponding activity levels (<emphasis>cf.</emphasis>
			<xref linkend="fig_animation" xrefstyle="select:label" />).</para>
		<figure id="fig_animator">
			<title>The animation plugin</title>
			<mediaobject id="animator">
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/animator.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para condition="html"><ulink url="javascript:show('animator')">Show animation</ulink></para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>To follow a trajectory in the state transition graph, select a starting state. It
			is then colorized in blue and added to the trajectory (listed in the animation
			dialog box). Its successor states are highlited, and can be added to the
			trajectory upon selection, which in turns changes the available successor states.</para>
		<para>To build another trajectory, select a state in the dialog and press the "&lt;&lt;"
			button to remove it and all of its successors.</para>
		<para>To view the defined trajectory, select the starting state and press the "|&gt;"
			button.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_gnuplot">
		<title>Trajectory visualisation with gnuplot</title>
		<para><phrase id="gnuplot"/>A path created with the animation plugin or found by the path
			finder can be visualized using <ulink url="http://www.gnuplot.info/">gnuplot</ulink>.
			The "GP" button (in the path finder and in the animator box) opens the gnuplot export box 
			(<xref linkend="fig_gnuplot" xrefstyle="select:label" />).
		</para>
		<figure id="fig_gnuplot">
			<title>Gnuplot export box</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/gnuplotExport.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>The gnuplot export box enables the selection of the kind of graph to create
				as well as the genes to display.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>After selecting the kind of output and the genes to display, click "export" and choose a place to save the plot.
		Note that two files are created but only the first file name is prompted for.
		If this filename is "myplot.gnuplot", the second file will then be named	"myplot.data".
		The actual graph can then be displayed using the command
		<emphasis>load "mygraph.gnuplot"</emphasis> at the gnuplot prompt.</para>
		<figure id="fig_gnuplotResults">
			<title>gnuplot export examples</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/gnuplot.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>Examples of the two kinds of gnuplot graphs. The first one
					uses arrows of different colors to show changes in the expression levels.
					The second one show separate subgraphs for each gene.</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
</section>

