<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"> 

<section id="sec_analyseRegGraph">
	<?dbhtml filename="analyseRegulatoryGraph.html"?>
	<title>Analysing the regulatory graph</title>
	<section id="sec_stableStates" xreflabel="stable states">
		<title>Stable State Search</title>
		<para>The <emphasis>Stable States</emphasis> option of the <emphasis>Actions</emphasis>
			menu allows the analytic (<emphasis>i.e.</emphasis> without running a simulation) determination of stable
			states of the model. All stable states are determined, regardless of their
			reachability, using an algorithm described in <xref linkend="Naldi2007"/>. The
			stable states dialog box (see <xref linkend="fig_stableStates"
				xrefstyle="select:label"/>) allows to run the analysis after the optional
			selection of a mutant. The result is shown in a table in the same dialog box, allowing
			to launch a novel analysis for another mutant. A "*" in the table denotes that
			each of the values of this component gives rise to a stable state (or several if another
			"*" appears in the same row).</para>
		<figure id="fig_stableStates">
			<title>The stable states dialog box, showing the result of the analysis</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/stableStates.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption/>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_circuits" xreflabel="functionality domains of regulatory circuits">
		<title>Functionality of Regulatory Circuits</title>
		<para> Regulatory circuits play crucial roles in the dynamical behaviour of a system.
			Indeed, positive circuits are required for the existence of several attractors, whereas negative
			circuits may generate cyclic attractors <xref linkend="Thieffry2007"/>. In <xref linkend="Naldi2007"/>, we 
			describe a method to analyse the dynamical roles of regulatory circuits.
			An implementation of this analysis is available in GINsim using the
			<emphasis>Circuits Functionality</emphasis> option of the <emphasis>Action</emphasis>
			menu (see <xref linkend="fig_circuits" xrefstyle="select:label"/>).
		</para>
		<figure id="fig_circuits">
			<title>Finding and analysing regulatory circuits</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/circuitsConfig.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>A first dialog enables to select which circuits will be analysed, by specifying
					constraints on the length of the circuits or on the involved actors. By default all
					circuits are considered.
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/circuits.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>When this first step is completed, the second dialog shows the list of circuits and
					enables to run the analysis. When the analysis is completed, new branches then displays 
					the functional circuits, classified according to their signs.
					When a circuit is selected, its functionality context is shown at the bottom of the dialog box.
					The analysis can be performed for the wild type model or for any predefined mutant.
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_pn" xreflabel="Petri net">
		<title>Petri Net Export</title>
		<para>
			Regulatory graphs can be exported into discrete <!-- TODO: check nomenclature with claudine -->
			Petri net using the rewriting method described in <xref linkend="Chaouiya2006"/>.
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>The Petri Net export dialog</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="../figures/pnexport.png"/>
				</imageobject>
				<caption>The Petri Net export dialog box allows to select the export format, the initial markup and the 
					mutant to apply before exporting. The initial markup can be generated from an existing initial state
					of the model  (modifications made in this dialog are also applied to the simulation settings); only the 
					first selected state is used.
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</section>
	<section id="sec_cytoscape" xreflabel="Cytoscape export">
		<title>Cytoscape Export</title>
		<para>
			Regulatory graphs can be exported to the <ulink url="http://www.cytoscape.org/">cytoscape</ulink> format.
			As cytoscape is not a modelling tool, this export only preserves the structure and appareance of the graph,
			not the logical parameters.
			An experimental cytoscape plugin is available on request to perform the complementary operation
			(i.e. export a cytoscape model into GINML).
		</para>
	</section>
</section>

